then you're qualified to do this first
meditation that all the seven-year-olds
learn
which is Tomlin okay okay so the
implication is
you need a lot of preliminary work
to do donut is not easy Tong Lan is a
very advanced practice
and you need a lot of
contemplations and meditations before
that okay and we'll do some
okay uh
you wanna let's do one right now okay
so get ready to meditate well grandpa
will lead you in a short meditation
those Vietnamese people call me omnoi
which means wise one I think
Grandpa
we'll do about 10 minutes uh
when you meditate in a group
you have a bigger obligation too
turn off yourself
be quiet yeah if your cell phone's not
off
blow your nose now
okay here we go
this week I'm gonna uh I want you to try
on
a new
uh
way to start a meditation which is a
hundred breath instead of ten
and uh I don't know if I'm getting more
distracted as I get older but I 10
breaths doesn't work for me and doing 10
breaths four or five times doesn't work
for me
100 doesn't work that's about six
minutes or something okay
so we're gonna do try to count 100
breaths
you're allowed to continue if you go off
just try to remember where you were
so here we go 100 breath
[Music]
exhales the first half inhales the
second hand
now I'd like you to think about
some interaction you had with someone
probably yesterday
but somebody who spent maybe half an
hour with in the last few days
and just try to choose one of those
interactions with another person at
least half an hour that you spent
together
and try to remember what it was that you
were hoping to get out of that
interaction like I I
spent uh the last five days with my wife
we went to take care of my mom who had a
stroke and uh
I was spending a lot of time with
Veronica and
I think I was
hoping to
ask hoping to work on sugang's text
so that was kind of in the back of my
mind
what were you thinking about
when you were with this person
what were you
what did you want to do during that time
and then what do you think the other
person wanted to do during that time
what what
based on what they spoke and based on
how they were acting
what did you what do you guess they most
wanted to do
while you were together what was in
their mind
and what would they enjoy what would
they have enjoyed doing
that time you were together
I think my wife at that time she was
really focused on helping my mom and
um
she has a list of other people that
she's helping and I think she would have
liked to have
really focused our time on that
and you could
sacrifice what you wanted to do
and you could just do what the other
person wanted to do
uh and that probably won't
be sustainable you probably cannot
continue doing that you also have
important things to do you have
things that you would like to do
and then they have things that they
would like to do
so
could there be a third
alternative and bodhisattvas
are constantly thinking
of somebody means is there a third
choice
I know what my wife would like to do
today
I know what I would like to do today
and is there some kind of clever
Innovative creative way
that we could both do what we want
and be together and and still be
interacting
and still spend the day together is
there some way
that we could both do
deeply get into what we want
individually
and
create some third possibility of
our relationship or our interaction
where somehow we do both
at the same time better
than if we were not together
is there some way
that I could
work on some gangster translation and
is there a way that we could be serving
my mom in
in my wife's other
clients
and uh is there some way that we could
do both
at the same time we have an equal right
to do what we would like to do
and is there's some really super
creative way
that we could help each other
do what each of us wants to do
and do it better
than if we tried to do what we want
alone
or at the expense of the other person
and this is the body's office
way of life they are not
sacrificing what they would like to do
they are not selfishly just doing what
they would like to do
they are finding creative ways
that everyone can get what they want at
the same time
so think about that interaction and
think of try to think of a third
choice between the two choices
something
way that you could have
achieved
what both people wanted
during the same day
so what my wife and I did
we blocked out a time in the morning she
enjoys walking and
we were in California she enjoys
walking out the at the ocean
so she would go for a walk
we just make a deal
and she might be collecting her thoughts
for the day or she might be
preparing
her list of things to do today to help
other people
and then during that time I I will work
on silkang's great translation
and uh
then we get together
at the end of the morning
we combine our lists
she has a list of people she would like
to
for us to help together and I have my
own list
so we spend a few minutes
combining our list
and fight working on a way that we can
do both during the day
together
try to think if there's some kind of way
you could have done that with this other
person
in your interaction this week it's it's
called
it's called
creative
Super Creative uh
middle way
between doing what they want
only what they want and doing only what
you want is there some
super creative way to
do both
and no person sacrifices each person's
goals for the day are equally important
and then slowly open your eyes come back
take a stretch
appreciate
and then I I think if you're like me uh
so I I used to have I remember when I
came to Dime Mountain first I had
um
80 students in New York
uh
and we came here to
to learn Diamond way together
they did uh seven years of preparation
in New York and then we came here and we
did seven years
uh of diamond way and then we all
graduated uh a lot of people did three
year retreat
uh
now it's two hundred thousand students
uh in the world so there are two hundred
thousand uh students in the there's
about 15 organizations no
and there's about uh 200 000 students uh
so I have these demands on my time it
went from 80 to 200 000.
uh and I have
the demands on my my time are are you
know
about that much more
you know uh
and I can't uh
I can't do what I do with my wife you
know I can't try to do what 200 000
people
would like
the way I used to do with 80 people you
know so unfortunately I have friends
many friends in this room from the 80
people days
and they're like could I just have an
hour of your time getting on I'm like no
things have changed you know
but uh
by the way I will spend time and I do
spend time and I you know I always have
time somehow
but uh you can't
accommodate 200 000 people the way you
can 80 people it's not possible
and I'm not saying you should go crazy
and try to give an hour to two hundred
thousand people we calculated it the
other day
it would take 16 years or something
uh 16.6 years uh so
it's not about that it's not a more
clever time management
time is also empty
time can also be bent and shortened or
lengthened Einstein proved it with
Mercury
traveling around the Sun
and the light that comes from Mercury to
the Earth
is Bent by the gravity of the Sun
so it can be proven as Einstein
predicted
that uh the light Mercury seems to slow
down as it exits the Arc of the Sun and
uh
time slows down time is a circle
space is curved
and it takes longer for light to get to
us if it has to pass by the sun which
means you are looking at the past
you are traveling in the past when you
look at mercury in a telescope literally
you are traveling in the past uh you
time travel
uh
and the new web telescope is just even
more
it's even more the case you can be in
the past you can observe the past
directly
as it happens uh and so
the bodhisattva's method
to accommodate
all people equally
has to do with emptiness of time and
space okay
we find time we create time
and we and we mess with I almost said a
bad word we mess with space and then we
can serve more people so the two kinds
of bodhichitta dovetail
kinds of body to help each other
it's it's impossible
for me in a normal time space to do what
I used to do
and it's impossible to accommodate
twenty two hundred thousand people the
way I accommodate my wife this week
unless I can work with emptiness okay so
you need that tool if you wanna in my
opinion
the reason he started the discussion
by saying the fake body tuner
was he was implying you got to use the
ultimate body Channel also or you cannot
ever
serve
people equally okay you cannot
accommodate
countless beings
wishes for equal time
unless you can mess with time
okay and you get better at it okay
you'll get better at it the first uh
the desire has to be there
to help
hundreds of thousands of people the
first the desire has to be there and
then that drives you what's it necessity
is the mother of invention you know if
you're hungry enough
to serve hundreds of thousands of people
you will find a way because the human
mind is
the capacity Your Capacity to serve
others is infinite you literally have an
infinite capacity you just have to
be pushed to it
okay good
all right we'll talk more about it